Chapter XLVI.
ELIZABETH had been a good deal disappointed in not finding a letter from Jane on their
first arrival at Lambton; and this disappointment had been renewed on each of the mornings that
had now been spent there; but on the third her repining was over, and her sister justified,
by the receipt of two letters from her at once, on one of which was marked that it had
been mis-sent elsewhere.
Elizabeth was not surprised at it, as Jane had written the direction remarkably ill.
They had just been preparing to walk as the letters came in; and her uncle and aunt, leaving
her to enjoy them in quiet, set off by themselves.
The one mis-sent must be first attended to; it had been written five days ago.
The beginning contained an account of all their little parties and engagements, with
such news as the country afforded; but the latter half, which was dated a day later,
and written in evident agitation, gave more important intelligence.
It was to this effect:— “Since writing the above, dearest Lizzy,
something has occurred of a most unexpected and serious nature; but I am afraid of alarming
you—be assured that we are all well.
What I have to say relates to poor Lydia.
An express came at twelve last night, just as we were all gone to bed, from Colonel Forster,
to inform us that she was gone off to Scotland with one of his officers; to own the truth,
with Wickham!
Imagine our surprise.
To Kitty, however, it does not seem so wholly unexpected.
I am very, very sorry.
So imprudent a match on both sides!
But I am willing to hope the best, and that his character has been misunderstood.
Thoughtless and indiscreet I can easily believe him, but this step (and let us rejoice over
it) marks nothing bad at heart.
His choice is disinterested at least, for he must know my father can give her nothing.
Our poor mother is sadly grieved.
My father bears it better.
How thankful am I, that we never let them know what has been said against him; we must
forget it ourselves.
They were off Saturday night about twelve, as is conjectured, but were not missed till
yesterday morning at eight.
The express was sent off directly.
My dear Lizzy, they must have passed within ten miles of us.
Colonel Forster gives us reason to expect him here soon.
Lydia left a few lines for his wife, informing her of their intention.
I must conclude, for I cannot be long from my poor mother.
I am afraid you will not be able to make it out, but I hardly know what I have written.”
Without allowing herself time for consideration, and scarcely knowing what she felt, Elizabeth,
on finishing this letter, instantly seized the other, and opening it with the utmost
impatience, read as follows: it had been written a day later than the conclusion of the first.
“By this time, my dearest sister, you have received my hurried letter; I wish this may
be more intelligible, but though not confined for time, my head is so bewildered that I
cannot answer for being coherent.
Dearest Lizzy, I hardly know what I would write, but I have bad news for you, and it
cannot be delayed.
Imprudent as a marriage between Mr. Wickham and our poor Lydia would be, we are now anxious
to be assured it has taken place, for there is but too much reason to fear they are not
gone to Scotland.
Colonel Forster came yesterday, having left Brighton the day before, not many hours after
the express.
Though Lydia’s short letter to Mrs. F. gave them to understand that they were going to
Gretna Green, something was dropped by Denny expressing his belief that W. never intended
to go there, or to marry Lydia at all, which was repeated to Colonel F., who, instantly
taking the alarm, set off from B., intending to trace their route.
He did trace them easily to Clapham, but no farther; for on entering that place, they
removed into a hackney-coach, and dismissed the chaise that brought them from Epsom.
All that is known after this is, that they were seen to continue the London road.
I know not what to think.
After making every possible inquiry on that side London, Colonel F. came on into Hertfordshire,
anxiously renewing them at all the turnpikes, and at the inns in Barnet and Hatfield, but
without any success,—no such people had been seen to pass through.
With the kindest concern he came on to Longbourn, and broke his apprehensions to us in a manner
most creditable to his heart.
I am sincerely grieved for him and Mrs. F.; but no one can throw any blame on them.
Our distress, my dear Lizzy, is very great.
My father and mother believe the worst, but I cannot think so ill of him.
Many circumstances might make it more eligible for them to be married privately in town than
to pursue their first plan; and even if he could form such a design against a young woman
of Lydia’s connections, which is not likely, can I suppose her so lost to everything?
Impossible!
I grieve to find, however, that Colonel F. is not disposed to depend upon their marriage:
he shook his head when I expressed my hopes, and said he feared W. was not a man to be
trusted.
My poor mother is really ill, and keeps her room.
Could she exert herself, it would be better, but this is not to be expected; and as to
my father, I never in my life saw him so affected.
Poor Kitty has anger for having concealed their attachment; but as it was a matter of
confidence, one cannot wonder.
I am truly glad, dearest Lizzy, that you have been spared something of these distressing
scenes; but now, as the first shock is over, shall I own that I long for your return?
I am not so selfish, however, as to press for it, if inconvenient.
Adieu!
I take up my pen again to do, what I have just told you I would not; but circumstances
are such, that I cannot help earnestly begging you all to come here as soon as possible.
I know my dear uncle and aunt so well, that I am not afraid of requesting it, though I
have still something more to ask of the former.
My father is going to London with Colonel Forster instantly, to try to discover her.
What he means to do, I am sure I know not; but his excessive distress will not allow
him to pursue any measure in the best and safest way, and Colonel Forster is obliged
to be at Brighton again to-morrow evening.
In such an exigence my uncle’s advice and assistance would be everything in the world;
he will immediately comprehend what I must feel, and I rely upon his goodness.”
“Oh! where, where is my uncle?”
cried Elizabeth, darting from her seat as she finished the letter, in eagerness to follow
him, without losing a moment of the time so precious; but as she reached the door, it
was opened by a servant, and Mr. Darcy appeared.
Her pale face and impetuous manner made him start, and before he could recover himself
enough to speak, she, in whose mind every idea was superseded by Lydia’s situation,
hastily exclaimed, “I beg your pardon, but I must leave you.
I must find Mr. Gardiner this moment on business that cannot be delayed; I have not an instant
to lose.”
“Good God!
what is the matter?”
cried he, with more feeling than politeness; then recollecting himself, “I will not detain
you a minute; but let me, or let the servant, go after Mr. and Mrs. Gardiner.
You are not well enough; you cannot go yourself.”
Elizabeth hesitated; but her knees trembled under her, and she felt how little would be
gained by her attempting to pursue them.
Calling back the servant, therefore, she commissioned him, though in so breathless an accent as
made her almost unintelligible, to fetch his master and mistress home instantly.
On his quitting the room, she sat down, unable to support herself, and looking so miserably
ill, that it was impossible for Darcy to leave her, or to refrain from saying, in a tone
of gentleness and commiseration, “Let me call your maid.
Is there nothing you could take to give you present relief?
A glass of wine; shall I get you one?
You are very ill.”
“No, I thank you,” she replied, endeavouring to recover herself.
“There is nothing the matter with me.
I am quite well, I am only distressed by some dreadful news which I have just received from
Longbourn.”
She burst into tears as she alluded to it, and for a few minutes could not speak another
word.
Darcy, in wretched suspense, could only say something indistinctly of his
“I have not an instant to lose” concern, and observe her in compassionate
silence.
At length she spoke again.
“I have just had a letter from Jane, with such dreadful news.
It cannot be concealed from anyone.
My youngest sister has left all her friends—has eloped; has thrown herself into the power
of—of Mr. Wickham.
They are gone off together from Brighton.
You know him too well to doubt the rest.
She has no money, no connections, nothing that can tempt him to—she is lost for ever.”
Darcy was fixed in astonishment.
“When I consider,” she added, in a yet more agitated voice, “that I might have
prevented it!
I who knew what he was.
Had I but explained some part of it only—some part of what I learnt, to my own family!
Had his character been known, this could not have happened.
But it is all, all too late now.”
“I am grieved, indeed,” cried Darcy: “grieved—shocked.
But is it certain, absolutely certain?”
“Oh, yes!
They left Brighton together on Sunday night, and were traced almost to London, but not
beyond: they are certainly not gone to Scotland.”
“And what has been done, what has been attempted, to recover her?”
“My father has gone to London, and Jane has written to beg my uncle’s immediate
assistance, and we shall be off, I hope, in half an hour.
But nothing can be done; I know very well that nothing can be done.
How is such a man to be worked on?
How are they even to be discovered?
I have not the smallest hope.
It is every way horrible!”
Darcy shook his head in silent acquiescence.
“When my eyes were opened to his real character, oh! had I known what I ought, what I dared
to do!
But I knew not—I was afraid of doing too much.
Wretched, wretched mistake!”
Darcy made no answer.
He seemed scarcely to hear her, and was walking up and down the room in earnest meditation;
his brow contracted, his air gloomy.
Elizabeth soon observed, and instantly understood it.
Her power was sinking; everything must sink under such a proof of family weakness, such
an assurance of the deepest disgrace.
She could neither wonder nor condemn; but the belief of his self-conquest brought nothing
consolatory to her bosom, afforded no palliation of her distress.
It was, on the contrary, exactly calculated to make her understand her own wishes; and
never had she so honestly felt that she could have loved him, as now, when all love must
be vain.
But self, though it would intrude, could not engross her.
Lydia—the humiliation, the misery she was bringing on them all—soon swallowed up every
private care; and covering her face with her handkerchief, Elizabeth was soon lost to everything
else; and, after a pause of several minutes, was only recalled to a sense of her situation
by the voice of her companion, who, in a manner which, though it spoke compassion, spoke likewise
restraint, said,— “I am afraid you have been long desiring
my absence, nor have I anything to plead in excuse of my stay, but real, though unavailing
concern.
Would to Heaven that anything could be either said or done on my part, that might offer
consolation to such distress!
But I will not torment you with vain wishes, which may seem purposely to ask for your thanks.
This unfortunate affair will, I fear, prevent my sister’s having the pleasure of seeing
you at Pemberley to-day.”
“Oh, yes!
Be so kind as to apologize for us to Miss Darcy.
Say that urgent business calls us home immediately.
Conceal the unhappy truth as long as it is possible.
I know it cannot be long.”
He readily assured her of his secrecy, again expressed his sorrow for her distress, wished
it a happier conclusion than there was at present reason to hope, and, leaving his compliments
for her relations, with only one serious parting look, went away.
As he quitted the room, Elizabeth felt how improbable it was that they should ever see
each other again on such terms of cordiality as had marked their several meetings in Derbyshire;
and as she threw a retrospective glance over the whole of their acquaintance, so full of
contradictions and varieties, sighed at the perverseness of those feelings which would
now have promoted its continuance, and would formerly have rejoiced in its termination.
If gratitude and esteem are good foundations of affection, Elizabeth’s change of sentiment
will be neither improbable nor faulty.
But if otherwise, if the regard springing from such sources is unreasonable or unnatural,
in comparison of what is so often described as arising on a first interview with its object,
and even before two words have been exchanged, nothing can be said in her defence, except
that she had given somewhat of a trial to the latter method, in her partiality for Wickham,
and that its ill success might, perhaps, authorize her to seek the other less interesting mode
of attachment.
Be that as it may, she saw him go with regret; and in this early example of what Lydia’s
infamy must produce, found additional anguish as she reflected on that wretched business.
Never since reading Jane’s second letter had she entertained a hope of Wickham’s
meaning to marry her.
No one but Jane, she thought, could flatter herself with such an expectation.
Surprise was the least of all her feelings on this development.
While the contents of the first letter remained on her mind, she was all surprise, all astonishment,
that Wickham should marry a girl whom it was impossible he could marry for money; and how
Lydia could ever have attached him had appeared incomprehensible.
But now it was all too natural.
For such an attachment as this, she might have sufficient charms; and though she did
not suppose Lydia to be deliberately engaging in an elopement, without the intention of
marriage, she had no difficulty in believing that neither her virtue nor her understanding
would preserve her from falling an easy prey.
She had never perceived, while the regiment was in Hertfordshire, that Lydia had any partiality
for him; but she was convinced that Lydia had wanted only encouragement to attach herself
to anybody.
Sometimes one officer, sometimes another, had been her favourite, as their attentions
raised them in her opinion.
Her affections had been continually fluctuating, but never without an object.
The mischief of neglect and mistaken indulgence towards such a girl—oh!
how acutely did she now feel it!
She was wild to be at home—to hear, to see, to be upon the spot to share with Jane in
the cares that must now fall wholly upon her, in a family so deranged; a father absent,
a mother incapable of exertion, and requiring constant attendance; and though almost persuaded
that nothing could be done for Lydia, her uncle’s interference seemed of the utmost
importance, and till he entered the room the misery of her impatience was severe.
Mr. and Mrs. Gardiner had hurried back in alarm, supposing, by the servant’s account,
that their niece was taken suddenly ill; but satisfying them instantly on that head, she
eagerly communicated the cause of their summons, reading the two letters aloud, and dwelling
on the postscript of the last with trembling energy.
Though Lydia had never been a favourite with them, Mr. and Mrs. Gardiner could not but
be deeply affected.
Not Lydia only, but all were concerned in it; and after the first exclamations of surprise
and horror, Mr. Gardiner readily promised every assistance in his power.
Elizabeth, though expecting no less, thanked him with tears of gratitude; and all three
being actuated by one spirit, everything relating to their journey was speedily settled.
They were to be off as soon as possible.
“But what is to be done about Pemberley?”
cried Mrs. Gardiner.
“John told us Mr. Darcy was here when you sent for us;—was it so?”
“Yes; and I told him we should not be able to keep our engagement.
That is all settled.”
“What is all settled?”
repeated the other, as she ran into her room to prepare.
“And are they upon such terms as for her to disclose the real truth?
Oh, that I knew how it was!”
But wishes were vain; or, at best, could serve only to amuse her in the hurry and confusion
of the following hour.
Had Elizabeth been at leisure to be idle, she would have remained certain that all employment
was impossible to one so wretched as herself; but she had her share of business as well
as her aunt, and amongst the rest there were notes to be written to all their friends at
Lambton, with false excuses for their sudden departure.
An hour, however, saw the whole completed; and Mr. Gardiner, meanwhile, having settled
his account at the inn, nothing remained to be done but to go; and Elizabeth, after all
the misery of the morning, found herself, in a shorter space of time than she could
have supposed, seated in the carriage, and on the road to Longbourn.
CHAPTER XLVII.
“I HAVE been thinking it over again, Elizabeth,” said her uncle, as they drove from the town;
“and really, upon serious consideration, I am much more inclined than I was to judge
as your eldest sister does of the matter.
It appears to me so very unlikely that any young man should form such a design against
a girl who is by no means unprotected or friendless, and who was actually staying in his Colonel’s
family, that I am strongly inclined to hope the best.
Could he expect that her friends would not step forward?
Could he expect to be noticed again by the regiment, after such an affront to Colonel
Forster?
His temptation is not adequate to the risk.”
“Do you really think so?”
cried Elizabeth, brightening up for a moment.
“Upon my word,” said Mrs. Gardiner, “I begin to be of your uncle’s opinion.
It is really too great a violation of decency, honour, and interest, for him to be guilty
of it.
I cannot think so very ill of Wickham.
Can you, yourself, Lizzie, so wholly give him up, as to believe him capable of it?”
“Not perhaps of neglecting his own interest.
But of every other neglect I can believe him capable.
If, indeed, it should be so!
But I dare not hope it.
Why should they not go on to Scotland, if that had been the case?”
“In the first place,” replied Mr. Gardiner, “there is no absolute proof that they are
not gone to Scotland.”
“Oh, but their removing from the chaise into a hackney coach is such a presumption!
And, besides, no traces of them were to be found on the Barnet road.”
“Well, then,—supposing them to be in London—they may be there, though for the purpose of concealment,
for no more exceptionable purpose.
It is not likely that money should be very abundant on either side; and it might strike
them that they could be more economically, though less expeditiously, married in London,
than in Scotland.”
“But why all this secrecy?
Why any fear of detection?
Why must their marriage be private?
Oh, no, no—this is not likely.
His most particular friend, you see by Jane’s account, was persuaded of his never intending
to marry her.
Wickham will never marry a woman without some money.
He cannot afford it.
And what claims has Lydia, what attractions has she beyond youth, health, and good humour,
that could make him for her sake forego every chance of benefiting himself by marrying well?
As to what restraint the apprehensions of disgrace in the corps might throw on a dishonourable
elopement with her, I am not able to judge; for I know nothing of the effects that such
a step might produce.
But as to your other objection, I am afraid it will hardly hold good.
Lydia has no brothers to step forward; and he might imagine, from my father’s behaviour,
from his indolence and the little attention he has ever seemed to give to what was going
forward in his family, that he would do as little and think as little about it, as any
father could do, in such a matter.”
“But can you think that Lydia is so lost to everything but love of him, as to consent
to live with him on any other terms than marriage?”
“It does seem, and it is most shocking, indeed,” replied Elizabeth, with tears in
her eyes, “that a sister’s sense of decency and virtue in such a point should admit of
doubt.
But, really, I know not what to say.
Perhaps I am not doing her justice.
But she is very young: she has never been taught to think on serious subjects; and for
the last half year, nay, for a twelvemonth, she has been given up to nothing but amusement
and vanity.
She has been allowed to dispose of her time in the most idle and frivolous manner, and
to adopt any opinions that came in her way.
Since the ——shire were first quartered in Meryton, nothing but love, flirtation,
and officers, have been in her head.
She has been doing everything in her power, by thinking and talking on the subject, to
give greater—what shall I call it?—susceptibility to her feelings; which are naturally lively
enough.
And we all know that Wickham has every charm of person and address that can captivate a
woman.”
“But you see that Jane,” said her aunt, “does not think so ill of Wickham, as to
believe him capable of the attempt.”
“Of whom does Jane ever think ill?
And who is there, whatever might be their former conduct, that she would believe capable
of such an attempt, till it were proved against them?
But Jane knows, as well as I do, what Wickham really is.
We both know that he has been profligate in every sense of the word; that he has neither
integrity nor honour; that he is as false and deceitful as he is insinuating.”
“And do you really know all this?”
cried Mrs. Gardiner, whose curiosity as to the mode of her intelligence was all alive.
“I do, indeed,” replied Elizabeth, colouring.
“I told you the other day of his infamous behaviour to Mr. Darcy; and you, yourself,
when last at Longbourn, heard in what manner he spoke of the man who had behaved with such
forbearance and liberality towards him.
And there are other circumstances which I am not at liberty—which it is not worth
while to relate; but his lies about the whole Pemberley family are endless.
From what he said of Miss Darcy, I was thoroughly prepared to see a proud, reserved, disagreeable
girl.
Yet he knew to the contrary himself.
He must know that she was as amiable and unpretending as we have found her.”
“But does Lydia know nothing of this?
can she be ignorant of what you and Jane seem so well to understand?”
“Oh, yes!—that, that is the worst of all.
Till I was in Kent, and saw so much both of Mr. Darcy and his relation Colonel Fitzwilliam,
I was ignorant of the truth myself.
And when I returned home the ——shire was to leave Meryton in a week or fortnight’s
time.
As that was the case, neither Jane, to whom I related the whole, nor I, thought it necessary
to make our knowledge public; for of what use could it apparently be to anyone, that
the good opinion, which all the neighbourhood had of him, should then be overthrown?
And even when it was settled that Lydia should go with Mrs. Forster, the necessity of opening
her eyes to his character never occurred to me.
That she could be in any danger from the deception never entered my head.
That such a consequence as this should ensue, you may easily believe was far enough from
my thoughts.”
“When they all removed to Brighton, therefore, you had no reason, I suppose, to believe them
fond of each other?”
“Not the slightest.
I can remember no symptom of affection on either side; and had anything of the kind
been perceptible, you must be aware that ours is not a family on which it could be thrown
away.
When first he entered the corps, she was ready enough to admire him; but so we all were.